so yesterday we had the the angel was
telling us how great it is to do
mahamudra meditation which is the
subject of this text and this is the
most famous mam mudha text sometimes
it's called the root Muhammad or text
and so the angel was advertising it and
said oh if you do this Maha mudra then
sooner or later you'll see emptiness and
you will get a Buddha body but that
Buddha body never think that that Buddha
body is not coming from you okay
so never think that Buddha body is just
some outside thing it's also flowing
from your seeds okay
and to think otherwise it's a huge
obstacle you said I mean - getting it so
if you think there's some kind of Voodoo
hood that you're gonna achieve which is
not flowing from your own seeds in your
own mind like a pen then that's the
largest stuff you can have and then on
those words the devil makes his
appearance in the mind and and says well
that's means you would have to kick me
out of your mind forever and then he
starts explaining why you shouldn't do
that okay and then he she said he said
by the way I I'm here because of
dependent origination okay so to deny me
would be to deny the foundation of
Buddhism which is cause and effect so to
kick me out of the mind since I come
from cause and effect would be a big
mistake and but I do admit that the idea
that I'm I'm cause and effect and you
are the opposite which is saying nothing
exists ultimately I do admit for that
reason one of us would have to leave the
mind okay you're supposed to say no
it's a wrong argument okay
he's already showing his colors you see
he's his first argument is mistaken I'll
say it again I came into your mind from
cause and effect you want to kick out
everything that doesn't exist ultimately
one of us has to go not true the
opposite is true okay things work
because they don't have any nature of
their own things work because they are
coming from us not because they come
from their own side you see so it's it's
cool to say you know don't think things
don't work and things do come from cause
and effect okay I've been in the
gardener for the last few months so it's
easy for me okay here we go then the
angel says something you know the devil
is being clever which is what they do
and she responds in an equally clever
way and she says you claim to be cause
and effect but I don't believe cause and
effect who's talking the angel okay the
angel says I don't believe cause and
effect so you must leave he says I got
here too cause of the thing you have to
respect me she says you're not cause and
effect even nominally okay you are not a
cause and effect which is coming from my
mind which is completely false okay
her argument is completely false okay
there is a cause and effect and it's
coming from your mind okay and she says
no you're not causing effect even though
you're coming from my mind okay and then
we're kind of left what's she talking
about you know did she have some tequila
last night you know like it's confusing
you see then then it that's where we're
gonna pick up by the way I thought this
morning I cleaned up my notes and I
thought to send them
to you tomorrow okay anybody who wants
talk to Tim and I kind of wrote it out
as a flow because the poetry is
difficult so I'll give you the poetry
you'll get the poetry but I think you
need some kind of commentary I don't
think this text should be published as
just the poetry because unless you're
very familiar with Buddhism it's it
doesn't make much sense you would get
confused okay all right
mmm then she says so I just doesn't know
time on verse 30 and don't look at your
text okay because you'll know you can't
do both okay
look at it when you get home right big
chance of that
[Music]
there you go then she says there's a
problem with your version of cause and
effect okay
because your version in your version of
cause and effect when a cause makes a
result it does through through some
nature of its own which is to say fire
is hot from its own side okay it's the
nature of fire that it should be hot and
it's the nature of causes that they have
a power inside of them to do something
and at this point in DC I I would teach
what we call it aspirin you know we
would have a long discussion about why
aspirins works sometimes and they don't
work sometimes so Connie can tell you
what's the active ingredient in an
aspirin cox-2 inhibitor okay it took me
like three months to learn this word
cox-2 inhibitor is the active ingredient
in an aspirin and and when we teach DCI
we don't say cause-and-effect exist
suffix that we don't go there we just
say we just asked the audience is the
cox-2 inhibitor the active ingredient in
an aspirin and people will say yeah it
says that on the bottle then we'll say
is it actor no it's not sometimes it
doesn't work okay it says active
ingredient but it's alive
okay it's not active because it only
active sometimes okay then people say
well that's the way Aspen are why do you
expect an expert to work every time well
then go buy a car that works three days
a week you know I mean you'll take it
back right but an aspirin nobody takes
it back nobody goes back to what's it
called
Walgreens what's the other one CVS and
say I want half the money back half of
them worked in half of them didn't work
you see people always because your mom
taught you okay sorry ladies taught you
not to expect that the Aspen would work
every time
you asked your mom mom the Aspen didn't
take away him I can remember where I was
V in the hallway outside my little
brother's room she put me in his room
because I was sick and I remember asking
my mom you know the Aspen didn't work
maybe I should take some more and she
gave me another one and then then she
gave me what he called a cloth on my
head she said try this you know I said
well just give me another aspirin she
says then she said a deadly thing to me
she said what sometimes they don't work
don't expect them to work all the time
and then at that moment your mother had
the devil in her mind okay like it was
the devil talking you know don't expect
things to work every time you know
that's not how life works and because of
mother saying that the whole world is
satisfied with things that don't work
every time and we think it's
unreasonable to expect things to work
every time so the problem here with the
devil when he says I come from cause and
effect and she says you don't she means
you you don't come from causes that were
from their own side you see got it okay
he has already kind of agreed to the pen
he's already agreed that individual
items come from me but he didn't get the
step - okay which is that the
interaction between things is also
coming from you which means an aspirin
may not work all the time okay there's
no thing in cause and effect which is
inside the cause that makes it do
something okay so it's a second level of
emptiness understanding you start with
static objects by the way I took home
somebody's pen last night and I felt
guilty I don't want to not have pens the
rest of my life
okay thank you
once you get to understanding that
individual objects are coming from your
seeds then the second stage of
understanding is that the interaction
between those objects is also coming
from your seats okay so we're he's that
he's kind of saying how can I understand
the pen but you know when something
causes something else when you take an
aspirin and your headache goes away that
comes from the aspirin got it
okay that's and that's where they're
stuck and that's why she can say with
impunity you are causing effect but not
really okay you got that right but
you're still wrong okay because he feels
like the cause has something in it that
makes the result happen and then you can
go study in the gardener for the rest of
your life
and he he spent his whole life
explaining my causes don't come some
results okay all right
verse 31 your version of cause and
effect could never change okay
had it you know aspirin would always
stop headaches and no one would get
headaches and things would never change
first 30 - it would be immutable self
standing never stopping okay if things
worked from something inside them then
things would never change okay then she
says if you are living who's you if you
the devil are living in my head in a
network of cause and effect of the kind
of causal effect you described you
couldn't be here anyway
got it okay he's talking about how he
got into her head I mean there are head
okay and he says cuz causes make things
happen of their own accord they have
something in them that makes things
happen okay fire is hot in and of itself
okay he says that aspirin to work
because of the active ingredient
because you helped other people with
headaches in the past okay aspirants
work by the way that's what makes the
active ingredient active when it's
active okay our active ingredients ever
actor yes sometimes but only if you've
been helping other people with headaches
that's all got it
so she says if the it's the aspirin had
something in it that took headaches away
then you couldn't be in people's head
okay if causes had a power inside of
them that wasn't coming from us then you
wouldn't be here okay got it
next Nick knows what to do he's just not
you know it helps it there's a lot of
flies okay all right it just means he
got into our heads to cause an effect
that didn't have its own power you see
how did how did the delegate into your
head cuz he was there last lifetime okay
well how did get into your head then cuz
he was there the life because you kept
misunderstanding aspirins okay got it
you kept doing it so he's been in your
head but that causes you planted to keep
the devil in your head don't have a
power in them that's also coming from
you okay so she says you know if my goal
is to get you out of my head you just
helped me why cuz he claims to be cause
and effect but he claims it because in
effect where there's a cause with some
power in the cause okay
and if that's true he couldn't be there
and he he would kick himself out okay
alright you gotta follow it here okay
verse 35 she quotes Dharma Keerthi guess
the book yeah
from Antarctica the commentary on
accurate perception okay
and she quotes that to say that you know
if things are causing effect they cannot
be self existent okay so this is a case
where they're defining self existent
which is the big enemy in Buddhism as as
anything which is not cause and effect
where two things don't rely on each
other where an aspirin has its own power
inside and it doesn't come from your
efforts to be a good person okay got it
okay then she crossed shantideva
first 36 got Mamula mark bar ding
mermaids in my end very famous a CIA
class 10 or 12 12 got yeah good you
cannot understand emptiness if you don't
understand what's not there okay you can
never understand shanty Davis says don't
go trying to understand emptiness and
alas you can picture in your mind what a
thing would be if it existed from its
own sign okay what's an example that's
in a bottle that you buy at the
drugstore in Aspen that works because of
something inside the aspirin okay an
aspirin that works because of something
inside the aspirin is called in Buddhism
gacha gacha means when you say emptiness
it has to be something not there okay
the classic example is Geshe Michael in
a fit of generosity takes John Brady to
Cucina restaurant and offers to pay and
then reaches into it this is a DCI
example right
by the way DCI means can you present
Buddhism without a single Buddhist word
okay and I think in the last few months
the audiences have been three or four
thousand Muslims okay who you can't say
you can't say this is Buddhist you see
and so what's the example of gotcha in
DCI it's a
credit card okay I tell job ready in a
fit of generosity which I often do right
don't worry
like Phil right it was the two days ago
we like he paid my bill and I paid his
bill and the waitress I think she took
both of them anyway so I offer John I'll
pay for the bill let's go to Katina you
know and then when we get there I'm
there's a moment of emptiness okay
emptiness means you expect something to
be there but it's not there that's the
classic feeling you should have when you
have emptiness okay I the bill comes I
tell you know I make a big deal out of
it I always say give me the bill because
I want to impress everybody around at
other tables you know and then the lady
gives me the bill and I go and then when
you go like that and your hand hits the
bottom of the pocket you know that's how
emptiness should feel to you okay
something's not there that you thought
was there okay cool now mix gonna tell
me how you go deeper in that analogy
yeah the credit card that I don't find
in my pocket is that Discover card that
doesn't work anyway okay cuz emptiness
is always the absence of something that
didn't exist anyway okay got it
something you expected to be there but
wasn't there anyway and aspirin rich
beautiful an aspirin there has something
inside it that takes away your heading
okay doesn't exist
okay it's not there you go looking you
don't find it okay alright so that's a
shanti david verse 36 verse 37 she
quotes a commentary to arya davis four
hundred verses he's a number one
disciple of the Gardena okay two
thousand years ago and it's a commentary
to the four hundred verses of
never by it happens to be by
chandrakirti okay who wrote the most
famous book on emptiness and he says the
meaning of self-existent is that it
doesn't depend on something else tell me
what that means with an aspirin yeah
great
oh I could kiss you buddy to far away
and Veronica's here Scott told me it's
illegal to say that kind of stuff
nowadays okay cancel that
yeah
if the Aspen didn't depend on something
else which means if it didn't depend on
me helping someone else with a headache
okay it doesn't mean doesn't depend on
its chemicals that's not what we mean we
mean that's what the devil thought right
we're talking about an aspirin that
would work without me helping other
people with headaches okay and that's a
self existence so here's at verse 37 is
an important clarification of what it
means when you say self-existent and it
means it doesn't depend on anything else
but it doesn't mean depend on chemicals
it means
depend on you doing something nice for
somebody else you see anything opposite
of that is self-existent and that's what
emptiness is empty earth got it cool all
right
therefore okay since you devil are
advocating a cause and effect where the
causes have a power of their own you and
me are incompatible okay that's a big
theme in this text okay it's like
there's some married couple that can't
stay together anymore they just can't
live in the same house they keep
fighting okay their fundamental
viewpoint of reality is totally opposite
somebody has to go somebody has to leave
she says even you're even when you talk
about cause and effect you're messed up
okay even when you talk about you blah
blah about cause and effect but you
don't even understand
the cars you think causes have something
inside them that which is by the way why
did he put that in the text because all
Buddhists who talk about causing the
effect have the same wrong idea okay
step two wrong idea
Oh causing the effect comes from causes
that have something inside them wrong
okay got it
just not all right now then the devil
comes back with something so cute okay
39 38 verse 39 as he comes back okay so
it's a separate line so I treated as a
verse okay the devil comes back the
devil gets to say his piece right Shalu
super power right he gets to come back
and make his defense okay and he says
listen I've lived in your heart forever
you're supposed to be a nice person have
mercy
let me stay okay he's appealing to her
compassion look I've been here in your
heart in this heart and this makes heart
you know or anybody I've been in their
heart my whole life lifetime after
lifetime have mercy
let me stay and and the first punch in
Lama says okay he says never have that
kind of mercy
okay there's a limit to mercy there's a
limit to compassion okay be ruthless be
merciless be a terrorist against your
devil in your mind okay no quarter
what do you call fight to the death okay
one of us has to go so forget compassion
when you're dealing with your
misunderstanding okay forget any idea
that it would be something nice to give
him some slack okay don't don't let him
say anything okay
like these as I interrupt people too
much not too much it's constant
they never get to say anything then be
that way with the devil okay if he
starts to say but but did say you know
shut up you know don't let him talk in
your head what I would hope you get out
of these three days and why we're doing
the meditation that Tim did and why
we're doing the workshop that you're
gonna do after this while I go relax and
buy my Thanksgiving dinner stuff is that
I want you to crank up your shishun your
monitoring of your own mind I want you
to Mahamudra meditation system number
one you learn to listen to your own
thoughts okay because right now you are
in them and you are not listening to
them you got to get some distance from
your own mind you have to practice
listening to the internal discussion
that's the first step of Mohammed
Mohammed means get practice at listening
to your mind stop being inside the
conversation step away from the
conversation and observe the
conversation that's step number one
step number two do not show any mercy
towards thoughts of self existence okay
this didn't come from me if a single
thought comes in you're in the mental
conversation you're observing all day
right if a single thought comes up that
says I don't like this person they hurt
me then take the sword of wisdom and cut
his head off don't even let him go on
okay oh no but he hurt me you know he
decided he said blah blah blah you know
okay so in the text this is a military
context right we're not supposed to let
a self existent thought come into our
mind during the half hour that you're
meditating but why did he make it an
internal conversation
he wants us to do that meditation all
day all day okay
he's like saying because of the title
because of the format he's saying look
I'm not just talking during meditation
that you have to watch your tendency to
believe that things are not coming from
you
no I want you thinking about it all day
I want the watch your mind
tuned up a Buddhist should be super what
he called self conscious you see they
should be almost dysfunctional which is
true
they should be Oh guess what I'm
thinking this is that okay no okay but
now I'm thinking that no don't do that
then you can get a little frozen right
it can paralyze you I we all know
Buddhist the best Buddhists are
paralyzed
the other ones are or what the heck I'm
just gonna think these thoughts okay so
he wants you to tune up your awareness
of the conversation in your head and be
merciless when the mental conversation
goes - I don't like this person I will
have to talk to them I will have to you
know write a letter I'll have to do
something to stop this person you know
outside I will have to take some outer
means when you hear the devil talk like
that during the day if you're a
Mahamudra master you like shut up you
know
okay got it mercilessly don't let him
even get you a sentence be like does she
Michael interrupting everybody okay
don't let him get to a whole sentence
he's like yeah but this person you yeah
shut up
you know he's coming from you yeah but
shut up yeah shut up okay and that's
meditation that's Muhammad meditation
that's the goal getting paralyzed by
your mam mudha meditation is the goal of
these three days until you become so
dysfunctional that you think you're
going insane there's a very famous thing
with anger meditation where shantideva
teaches you how not to get angry and
then the student
back and says it didn't work in fact it
made me worse I'm worse than I was last
week after I came to your three-day
teaching my mind got worse than it was
before what a shantideva answer you were
just noticing what was always there for
the first time you're aware of how your
own mind is talking which is stupid okay
you're amazing yeah but gage not this
present didn't let me shut up okay I had
a t-shirt I designed a new t-shirt and
said Scott gave me one
it says shut up and do the force terms I
used to have a tape recorder in my
pocket and people demand five minutes
with me to discuss their unique personal
problem right and I was thinking to have
a tape recorder just as oh yes there's a
way to fix that try the four steps you
know and I I've repeated the first test
people pay how much got $1,700 an hour
at those special VIP events
Diamond Group depends on what country
they pay almost two thousand dollars an
hour to have me tell them the four steps
again ten minutes after they came out of
the public time you see what I mean okay
so just tell them to shut up okay but
you can't do that unless you're aware of
the conversation in your own mind okay
so the goal of these three days is that
you become more sensitive to the insane
conversation going on in your own mind I
don't this person hurt me or this
person's not cared or the way to fix
this problem is to talk to somebody okay
right okay all right so verse 40 the
devil's like have mercy your
compassionate person let me stay in this
person's heart okay don't kick me out
all right then
41 beautiful he says and in fact you
kick me out of this guy's heart he's
gonna have hard time getting the things
he needs in his
okay he won't get money he won't get
cars he won't get position he won't get
houses okay without me to protect this
guy he won't be able to get anything
he'll be giving away everything you know
he'll be shared his money with everybody
he'll be letting people sleep in his
house you know he'll be giving other
people the salary that he was supposed
to get you see I mean we can't without
me this guy's gonna have a hard life
okay right
that's his also first 42 this guy won't
be able to find friends you know it's me
that helps you find friends you see you
ignore other people you go get friends
you see I mean you have to without me as
a motivation you will not go to
nightclubs you will not go online to
look for friends okay you would just sit
at home and hope a friend came to you I
had a lady in New York she said I want
to have a partner you know so I said
look you don't get a partner by going
online you don't get a partner by going
to a nightclub you get a partner by
helping a lonely person you know she
said why I said they're coming from you
you know and we had a long conversation
I remember it was shortly after I came
to the place in Maryland I remember it
was like a day later this is like 20
years ago orsome and so she's like I
gotta talk about this you know I gotta I
gotta stretch this thing out and finally
at the end of the conversation she's
like so you're telling me that if I help
lonely people I will plant a karmic seed
in my mind that a partner will manifest
from my mind a real partner
you know like kissable partner you know
variable partner and I said yes she said
if that's true then if I lock myself in
my New York apartment for two weeks
after planting those seeds the guy
should show up in my apartment you know
with the door long I'm yes I'm like I
took a chance you know I said yeah
that's true she says I'm gonna you know
I'm gonna try it you know so she did she
went to her apartment she locked the
door okay this is true unbelievable
some guy knock on the door FedEx scary
okay she fell in love with him they got
married okay
I'm not kidding okay anyway it's true I
don't care if you don't believe me down
so that the devil is like without me to
chase people on the line without me to
motivate you to go to nightclubs you're
gonna be friendless you're gonna be
lonely okay if you follow this stupid
angel that says partners come from
karmic seeds you're gonna spend your
whole life in your house waiting for
someone to show up right that's his
position okay this lady's gonna paralyze
you you've got to get out there and do
it you know you need strategies for
relationships you know okay forget this
sister since that's okay for certain
things at certain times but don't go
crazy with it there's times when you
should just go do it you know right
that's his main thing that's his main
thing okay yeah okay you said Clint
clancy's once in a while for big stuff
but don't get anal about it you know
like don't think all day
you know I gotta plant seeds to get
breakfast you know I better make a
donation to charity tonight I gotta have
waffles in the morning okay like don't
go crazy about it be reasonable okay
who's that the devil wants you to be
reasonable and the devil objects if you
use these ideas every moment of the day
okay and that's the purpose of this text
it becomes a meditation because you're
following your thoughts constantly
moment a moment okay it's not an
occasional once every week you do a four
steps okay she's proposing that you do
it every
minions okay and I've taught people like
that nor is like then I had a discussion
with north in the Bucharest Airport with
all these Romanian guys and she's like
yeah I said how's it going here's my I
got this I'm like yeah okay and then I
did the first thing I got this you know
it's just like yeah I'm like well that's
nice you know and then she's like and
then I was the four steps on the first
dozen I got this you know and it was
just like after a while I'm like is
there anything you don't do with the
four steps like do you go to the
bathroom without the first dance she's
like well I haven't tried that one but
oftentimes you teach someone and they're
more conscious of it than you are
she's an example and her life is the
mate her life is like a dream yeah it
makes me want to try it okay all right
verse 43 devil sus the angel I think
it's a big mistake to think you're going
to switch me out for somebody else you
know I don't think it's reasonable okay
I think you should just keep me here
because you can't get friends you can't
get stuff without someone taking care of
your self interest don't spend all your
time taking care of other people there
has to be times when you take care of
yourself okay and that's who that's a
double talking okay alright hey verse 44
by the way we're warming up we're
starting to segue to the actual
mahamudra meditations okay you can heal
it coming because next he says listen
many people have tried to kick me out of
their mind in the past and they all
failed okay and even this person whose
mind I'm in right now they have made
feeble uneducated attempts to kick me
out and it never worked so just forget
it what you're trying to do today has
been done before
countless times this person met a
spiritual teacher this person learned
about things coming from them they tried
to kick me out and Here I am
10,000 lifetimes later I'm still here
okay so it's kind of foolish to kick me
out over the course of countless
lifetimes
I have given my blessing I have imparted
my demonic blessing to this mind and
it's gonna be this way forever okay
because my blessing stays got it kind of
depressing okay and then she's like but
she's like somebody trying to talk to
you Michael she's not and he runs over
her you know he says even body starts
eyes have me okay and that's true right
even a bodhisattva has a devil in them
right okay they they got the first big
shot in when they reached the first
place off the level and saw emptiness
directly they took a shot and they
damaged him but he's still there he says
listen if you know anything about
Buddhism who's talking the devil star
can hear you if you know anything about
Buddhism I stay in the people's mind
actively up to the seventh Bodhisattva
level and you cannot find a person in
this country more than a handful who've
reached the first Bodhisattva level so
what are the odds of getting rid of me
okay you carry me after the seventh body
something Lama okay you carry me up to
there there's no chance okay up to the
seventh buddy sign third level you do
have the seeds to see things that's
coming from their own side okay even
when you're explaining the pen to
another person and explaining why it
doesn't come from its own sign at that
moment because of the blessing of the
devil they are still seeing the pen as
coming from the pen while you're
explaining the pen for the 400th time to
a person they are still seeing that pen
as coming from its own sign okay until
the until you get through the seventh
buddy saw the Lama okay it's like
hopeless
so he's like what are the odds you're
gonna kick me out you know even hi buddy
Sabbath have me but buddy suffice that
haven't walked on this planet for
centuries you know still have me okay
all right number 46 and by the way the
stained okay that startled imprint to
believe that things are coming from
their own side last until the tenth
Bodhisattva level okay until the final
moment before enlightenment you still
have a subtle imprint it's called Meng
in limbo you still have a subtle imprint
in your mind where you could flip back
okay you still have that tendency carved
on your mind
okay so verse number 46 you know people
at the 10th political level have an
imprint for me spilling their mind what
hope will a non Bodhisattva have what
hope would a normal person have a
kicking me out of the mind get serious
who's talking the Dhamma and he's
correct okay we're just depressing then
she said verse 47 miss wisdom you only
visit this mind occasionally I have a
permanent resident card okay I'm a
permanent resident I've always been here
I have a green card for this mind okay I
get to stay here forever
okay Connie you're just a visitor your
honor 188 day visa okay or 180 seconds
these days you have to leave after those
three minutes insane I mean okay
all right and not only that verse 48
once I get into a mind I bring my
extended family okay it's like that
green card one person gets in what's it
called
chinma yeah
well we have going on in this mind
is chain migration you see well once I
get in and I get my green card then all
my friends come in and it's just like a
big party in this mind you know and then
he makes a list of his friends okay
ready here we go I bring in jealousy I
bring in refusal to share your things
with other people I bring in deceitful
behavior I bring in pretending to be
someone you're not
I bring in pride I bring in sixty five
versions of mistaken viewpoints about
reality I have an extended family you
know once I'm in the house you know
you're gonna kick all of them sound
I mean means means okay I mean maybe you
could maybe if you meditated really hard
every morning you could kick me out
maybe if you educate yourself with this
poem and then you worked hard on it
every morning maybe you and and worked
hard on it all day that you don't have
self-existent thoughts oh I'm gonna take
care I'm gonna make I'm gonna get this
goal by working hard or I'm gonna
connect with someone who could help me
okay those are who's talking demo that's
double talking okay I'm gonna I want to
get a certain financial goal you know I
would like to put this much money in the
bank okay well how you gonna do it then
the devil starts talking I should take
more of my money and put it in the bank
devil talking I should invest my money
in Bitcoin or whatever devil talking I
should work harder devil talking you
know I shouldn't give away so much money
devil devil talking okay all right and
in my dream of from this class what I
would like you to get from this class
don't put up with this kind of thinking
in your own mind even for five minutes
and that's gonna take a high degree of
shishun was watching your mind
thing okay watching the conversation in
your mind okay your mind has a ongoing
conversation for all the conscious hours
of your
okay but you're inside it you don't have
to be inside it step back
watch the mind talk and object when the
mind says something stupid okay Interop
be gushy Michael someone's trying to
tell you about their dying aunt and
you're like yeah but do you know how
many people came to Ukraine okay like
interruptus different minds right all
right everybody stop we don't get money
by saving money we get money by sharing
money okay just stop penance and
interrupt okay got it
that's the goal of this this is not
these three days are not to be limited
to meditation period okay that's a
mistake okay
outside of meditation periods hi debris
earth-shaking
awareness of what you're thinking
awareness of the conversation step back
and listen to how silly the conversation
is okay how how incredibly unburden it
is okay in a well-trained Buddhist mind
because you haven't been watching your
mind okay all right verse 49
I'm the permanent confidant of this
person when they have problems they come
to me to talk they don't come to you
you're a flash in the pan he calls her a
flash in the pan
you're like a stroke of lightning you
know in the whole 24 hours you like sit
and then you're gone you know somebody
can only think about you for about 30
seconds at a time and then they come
back to me for hour after hour take care
of yourself take care of number one
okay got it you're just like occasional
generosity thought maybe I should yeah
shut up let's take care of herself okay
okay then he says he accuses her okay
ready
he says listen I'm your little brother
we've been in the same line for whatever
you know where I've been here with you
I'm just part of the family okay I'm
just part of this person's mind I admit
you could come once in a while you
make your appearance for a day or two
and then go back home but you know I've
been here all along I'm not really
different from you we are both residents
you're just temporary I'm here all the
time taking care of the house you know
give me a little respect don't paint me
as a monster okay he says that don't
paint me with horns okay
I'm not such a devil okay I'm just
another member of the family who's
trying to make a living in the mind okay
so don't tell everybody I'm this monster
okay I'm just another guy trying to make
it okay it's very cute he says don't
force me away from the warmth of heart
and home hearth and home don't force me
away from the family fire I also need
warmth
I also need life I'm also surviving in
this mine get cut me some slack okay I'm
part of the family then she says yeah be
merciless be a warrior take recon
no quarter accept no quarter given the
quarter
yeah just if he starts to say but then
before he gets to the tea cut him okay
like at least try make some feeble
effort okay yeah but this guy gauge line
you don't understand this guy sitting is
shut up just shut up okay yeah okay at
least make some when he call it put up a
fight okay in a normal mind the devil
will prevail okay you get extra credit
for putting up a fight longer so fight
for those 30 seconds okay your mind is
like I should take the last doughnut
yeah but I should take the last donut
but what if we I should take the last
doughnut okay let's take the last night
okay
but you get so much karmic credit for
the
but okay it's a famous thing in a
British Scripture okay you get like a
thousand times
normal karmic seeds by resisting your
bad habits okay even if it's only for
ten seconds so I always stand there with
Veronica's pumpkin pie and I'm like I
know I'm gonna eat it but I'm just
waiting you know ting ting ting ting
more good things ting ting Jo okay so
just just hold off for a few seconds
okay and then those seeds accumulate and
then similar later you just set the pie
down I mean but you gotta resist your
bad habit for the few minutes that you
can and then go ahead and and indulge
okay okay all right now verse 51 more
sexy
okay ready I like this book can you tell
he's like look miss wisdom let's get one
thing straight who are you to fight
karma you know even Buddhists have to
respect karma when karma says
something's going to happen it happens
not even a Buddha can take away your bad
karma that's a famous Buddhist principle
okay with all the compassion that's
possible within a living mind a Buddha
cannot take a wine away one iota of your
karma it's not possible to taken away
another person's Karma as you sow you
shall reap and no one can take it away
so how did I get in this my Karma
who are you miss miss them to try to do
something no Buddha can do who are you
to override
who who the hell you think you are you
think you're bigger than a Buddha okay
how did I get in his mind karma by
respecting the laws of karma I arrived
okay this person refused to share what
they learn with other people because it
was inconvenient for them or those
people were irritating okay that's why
I'm still here they collected karma to
keep me in their mind who are you to say
we should cancel karma today okay not
even a Buddha can do who do you think
you are okay it's a beautiful line okay
I think you're better than Gautama you
gonna break karma when Gotham I couldn't
I I deserve to be here I'm here because
the person made the seeds to keep me
here that's just justice that's that's
universal justice I'm here because of
the universal laws of justice okay this
person whose mind were sharing deserves
me who are you to cancel that okay it's
a beautiful argument right who do you
think you are all right now our angel is
not a stupid angel our double is clever
but our angel is smart okay and she says
these arguments of yours are a guy
riding on a donkey to find the donkey
Nick explain do you know the story still
out wait who's he farmer yes
some Rancher is come up there's a
rancher who's riding on his horse and he
has a certain amount of horses that he's
supposed to count 50 horses he's
supposed to count each day and he keeps
counting the horses and he only gets 49
so he's riding around and he's counting
and he rides around the range and he
keeps counting he comes up with 49 and
he's scratching his head trying to
figure out where is the last horse okay
good it's a famous Tibetan junk Tibetan
humor is a really really strange okay
and they would be laughing they'd be
rolling in the aisles right now okay
anyway you mister devil are trying to
explain to me the laws of karma that you
accused me of breaking but if we are to
accept the laws of karma then you have
to leave because the real devil doesn't
understand the real laws of karma if if
you ever understood what you're talking
about it would result in your what's
that thing when they kick people out of
their apartment eviction okay got it
devil you better stop talking about
Karma
you better stop talking about cause and
effect because you are dangerously close
to understanding it which would result
in your eviction because you cannot stay
in a mind which understands karma got it
stop talking about Karma
stop lecturing me about Karma don't tell
me I can't break karma that the
Buddhists can cannot break okay because
if you keep going with this karma stuff
you've been evict your self got it I
like it all right okay and by the way
the only person that's really inherent
in the human mind is a Buddha
you want to talk about permanent
residents there is a permanent resident
in the mind of every living creature and
it is their enlightened nature okay
don't talk to me don't tell me you have
a green card
okay the ultimate green card citizenship
is enlightened state of mind all living
beings have an inherent enlightened
nature okay cool I like it she's so sexy
she's like stop talking about green
cards okay maybe you got a green card if
the Trump's gonna revoke all of them you
know you can't stay here but listen this
person's Buddha nature was born in this
country okay when they were born they
had a Buddha nature and they still have
it who wants to take a shot at
explaining Buddha nature to everybody
every okay words gonna dead come come on
okay quick quick we don't have much time
these are really short classes I'm gonna
make a statement you're gonna explain it
okay Randy every living creature has 25%
of their Buddhahood already okay go okay
because there's four bodies of the
Buddha or they say bodies but it means
like parts actually and one of those
parts is the emptiness of the Buddha
which is actually the emptiness of all
the bodies of the Buddha so inherent in
all beings is their own lack of self
nature which is their emptiness which is
one of the bodies of the Buddha
[Music]
and that's the only person who's allowed
to live in this mine by birth okay
they they're gonna stay you're not gonna
stay okay and then verse 55 okay she
says if I have my way then you're gonna
be homeless
okay it's kind of cruel language okay
and you okay
am i yeah if I have my way you will be a
homeless person shortly okay you will
have no place to live
okay and again it's this theme of be
merciless with those random thoughts
that come in your mind about how you're
gonna fix a problem with another person
without fixing yourself okay don't put
up with them okay be strict with them
later he's gonna say when your halt
right hungry angry lonely tired there's
another eh-eh-eh-eh alone when you're
alone you are more likely to entertain
thoughts of fixing your problems with
self-existent means I will talk to this
person I will write this letter you know
blah blah when you're tired hungry
lonely upset you can't think straight he
talks about it later
he supports how I found out recently it
comes from the 12-step okay so he says
she says be careful when you're hungry
lonely tired you've been upset be
careful that Bevo will sneak back in you
won't be able to think clearly okay
so get in a way it's almost useful to do
jetlag got to yourself constantly
because if you can think straight when
you have jet lag
you can think straight anytime you see
it I mean cool like that when you gets
charleen earth
put yourself purposely in stressful
situations to make yourself stronger
okay like go visit the person you don't
like and see if you can keep the devil
from talking the whole time and you
won't okay all right now she says you
are a monster and I didn't make you a
monster you made yourself a monster
you've proved yourself to be a monster
I'm gonna make you homeless now big
segue then the way for me to exclude you
from this mind by the way I had an idea
in in like six minutes we'll have 15
minutes left
I'll take questions okay any kind of
question we have a bunch of veteran
Buddhist here we have a lot of three or
retreatants here if you have any
question about anything okay it doesn't
have to be relevant I know it's not
gonna be relevant anyway so I'm just
giving you permission ask me any
question you want about your life or
about your challenges or something you
want to go you want to reach or
something about the theory of Buddhism
which seems to be you know it's kind of
bugging you for this this last day and a
half okay like something I said or okay
so so get ready okay in about six
minutes okay now she says it's time to
discuss your eviction and we're gonna do
it with the purse of emptiness okay now
big segue okay and this is kind of we're
going into the meat of the text okay she
says it's time to discuss your eviction
and what do you call the victors what
else guys there police come special
police the guys who repossess your car
marshals guys yeah sometimes they're
really sweet it's the weirdest thing you
know I have to revisit econ so sorry no
don't touch the car get away from the
car
so she says we're gonna do some logic
let's do some logic and then you'll
admit you have to leave okay here's the
first one and then verse 56 okay so I'm
just indexing it for the recording okay
then people can use the text later it
has a number on each verse so she says
by the time I finish giving you these
proofs for emptiness you will agree
delije you will stop struggling against
me you know they are so convincing these
Naggar Dooney and arguments that you
will you will voluntarily leave this
mind okay I I don't know about anyway
okay all right here we go and by the way
inherent in that argument is a deeper
argument in Buddhism okay you ready
inherent in her comments is a deeper
argument in Buddhism and I'll let me see
if I can remember the metaphor yeah I
got it yeah he just translated this part
so suppose you're walking down the road
and you look down and you see a snake
and you feel frightened and you're
walking with a friend and your friend
you know notices that you're frightened
and they're like oh don't worry it's
just a rope so they're telling you it's
a rope and then all of a sudden you feel
better you're like oh okay cool it's not
a snake I'm not going to get bit later
on you guys are walking back from the
same place you realize it was never a
rope in the first place it was just a
tree root that looks
a rope so the metaphor here the point is
that there is you understood it to be a
rope and it eased your fear but that was
still a mistaken idea so you're using a
mistake to heal your mind from one form
of pain but it still wasn't the truths
that was able to heal you good okay okay
[Applause]
yeah so I always picture this happening
at Diamond Mountain and you're walking
down a wash me and we were there we saw
a nice Gila monster one day
so anyway you're walking down one of
those washes at Diamond Mountain
you've just been discussing desert
willows okay you've just been discussing
desert willows okay like we were
discussing them on the way here right we
were discussing the difference of desert
willows so your mind is on desert Willis
okay and then you see a desert willow
root that looks like a snake and your
friend freaks out oh I'm almost stepping
on this snake but it's really just a row
okay it's really just the rope but
because you've just been discussing
desert willow roots you say don't worry
it's just a desert willow root okay are
you telling the truth no does it ease
the person's fear is it okay to do yeah
it's okay I mean morally it's okay why
are we talking about that as we discuss
these famous proofs for emptiness you
will misunderstand them the components
you will misunderstand the words you
will misunderstand the meaning you will
attribute self existence to every single
part of the explanation in your mind as
you as someone teaches you the pen is
taking the speaker and the pen and
yourself as coming from
mario's okay even as someone's teaching
you that they're coming from you okay
got it
the same applies to the classical
reasons with which we prove emptiness
well we're describing them in the next
few pages you will be actively
misunderstanding the elements but not
the intention
you will be misunderstanding the nature
of the words for example it's difficult
to appreciate when you're getting a good
explanation of emptiness that it's
coming from you okay it's almost
impossible to think that while someone's
explaining to you a proof of emptiness
that you thought you've never heard
before
okay people when you explain to them
that everything's coming from them one
of the most common questions we get in
DCI is how can I be creating the teacher
who's explaining these ideas to me which
I have never thought of what's the
answer you shared what you knew about
small things all seeds are smaller than
their results an oak an acorn weighs
half a gram an oak tree weighs 5,000
kilos okay so trying to help someone
else a little bit understand about karma
has resulted in you getting this
incredible explanation of Naggar Jeanine
Ian proofs of emptiness from the first
Panchen Lama in a school in Sedona in an
elementary schooler Donna you know you
must have some kind of rare disease okay
all right something that was born in
South India 2,000 years ago is echoing
back to you okay and and while it's that
going back to you from your own good
deeds you will misunderstand where it's
coming from
okay got it the reasoning that will free
you is enslaving you as we give it
something like that okay got it and
we're gonna pick up there this evening
we're gonna so I have to start this
evening with we're just gonna have two
proofs of emptiness which is kind of a
slow day in Buddhism and then and then
we'll have then we're going to go on to
26 wrong ideas about Muhammad or
meditation which which by the time we
end have brought you to correct Muhammad
or meditation by by by default we call
it by a process of elimination okay
hearing 26 things that it's not you can
probably come up with what it is on your
own okay got it
all right questions anybody it doesn't
have to be relevant yours are too hard
okay that's okay go ahead
hers are always the hardest thank you
for teaching give me a doc okay so
I'm wondering if you're using the same
you know you've just been talking about
how we're gonna misunderstand these
proofs of emptiness have have you been
using that same trick when you say that
the Buddha nature is inherent to us okay
good it okay
venerable palace question is I made a
statement that you know you already have
a Buddha nature which is inherent
meaning it has been in your mind forever
and it will be in your mind forever and
that's not the case with the devil okay
he's been there a long time
but his days are numbered okay now your
your Buddha nature though continues up
to the time you become a Buddha and
while you're a Buddha so it has no
beginning and it will have no end
so I described it as inherent but I mean
inherent to mean constantly accompanying
you and not that it doesn't come from
you ah okay but it's a good question so
I was using the word inherent to mean
that you've always had it and not to
imply
that it didn't come from you okay all
right next question I knew you're gonna
ask a hard question okay okay
online so we have someone from online
her name is Anna and she's from Romania
she said Kesha whatever we had a good
time in Romania it was a beautiful
beautiful problem she's scheduler what
is the difference between the gotcha and
emptiness okay good
what's the difference between the gotcha
and emptiness okay the gotcha in my
pocket is a credit card that wasn't
gonna be accepted by Cucina anyway you
see even if I hadn't changed my pants
just before I went out with John Brady
okay even if I had worn the old you know
grungy pants that I didn't change for a
couple weeks in the house okay even if I
had brought that credit card with me
Cucina being a rapid of the restaurant
doesn't accept the Discover card okay
all right got it so that's the gotcha
okay in the kitchen what's the gotcha a
husband who I didn't we can kind give it
a little more passion yeah good you got
to get whiny when you teach it
she's one of our teachers you got to do
it whiny okay you know who's really good
at that is ayrton in mexico you think I
need reading okay that kind of husband
is a guard job the husband who didn't
come from something you did in the past
the impossible husband is the karcher
okay
the emptiness is the fact that he was
never he said never in the kitchen he
isn't in the kitchen and he will never
be in the kitchen which means he is an
in the kitchen okay got it
so the emptiness is the fact that that
person
isn't in the kitchen there's no husband
like that in the kitchen okay not
possible
got it the gotcha is that imaginary
husband okay
he cannot exist but you can imagine him
okay so that's a big point you can
imagine him but he's not real can you
imagine a two-headed purple elephant yes
is it real no you can imagine the gotcha
but it's not something that exists okay
I wanted to say that most about that was
that hmm oh when does she perceive
emptiness in the kitchen yeah she's kind
of talking to herself
should I call him stupid back or is
there any reason why I shouldn't I'm
stupid bank and then she well-trained
Buddhist it because she's been thinking
about it constantly
there's no time gap she doesn't remember
that he doesn't exist two days later
after she screams back okay in the
moment as a well trained Buddhist it
comes on where is this coming from where
is this coming from and she's like no
you okay then at that moment
she's perceiving emptiness cool okay one
more we didn't I was late so let's go a
little bit late it's not okay all right
doctor more by the way dr. Marr and his
wife bunny have been grading papers
especially on prisoners around the world
for about 30 years and I'd like to thank
them for that
[Music]
[Applause]
and helping with innumerable projects I
got one more fee I'll tell you later
go ahead heed now he's scared so if a
karmic seed ripens a luminescence
essence comes out and it circles the
object and it says pin so they're shapes
and colors there
I didn't just put those there there are
shapes and colors there lower-middle way
this is called the raw data question ok
so the way that reality works is that
another person is holding an object that
has colors and shapes but the and in
Buddhism as well in the abhidharma kosha
in the second chapter the way that I
faculty works the power of the eye right
is that there are cells at the back of
the eye that respond to light and shape
and that's all they they're just like
bits on a computer they can say black or
white that they are limited to that they
cannot make decisions about what's out
there so technically your eye can only
detect differences in shape and color it
cannot decide this is a pen or that okay
the eye cannot do that in science they
would say the eye the optical nerve the
information travels up the Arctic nerve
to the brain and then the brain gets
this data and then the brain makes a
decision about what the thing might be
okay that's that's a science okay in in
Buddhism somebody is holding a long
green thing okay okay it's restricted to
two attributes one shape two color they
are holding a long green in the case of
scheria spin
okay you wanna hold your pen up there
yeah it's a distinctive yeah
so my is detecting long green okay
that's all that's all I can do okay my I
cannot do anything more than that then a
karmic seat opens in my mind a small
picture of a pen comes out and it glues
itself to that thing and I see a pen
okay and if you meditate everyday you
can see it happening and you don't have
to come to my class anymore okay well I
keep telling you what happens but you
can confirm it yourself don't don't just
sit around you know don't wait for me to
tell you something if you studied this
text well if you get a good explanation
if you meditate every day one day you
will see it you will actually see it at
what level second of the five Buddhist
path at the fourth level okay so
Michaels question is who put the green
and long there yeah you did in the
moment before okay you did do it in the
moment before okay middle waste coal
which is the highest of the four
classical schools of India the
lower-middle way says that the raw data
was out there it was out there and then
my mind interpreted so in a grand sense
don't think Buddhism's task is to
discuss the interpretation of objects
okay we're not saying Neil Young song
you know some people interpret it as as
as good and some people interpret it as
bad Buddhism is not about psychological
interpretation
it's about existence where did the Neil
Young song come from not that if you're
in a good mood it sounds good if you're
in a bad mood it doesn't sound so good
okay it's not done we are not talking
about psychological interpretation we're
not we're talking about who created it
who created Neil Young
got it yeah so it's a great question in
the moment before your mind creates that
which implies that before you walked
into the room there was no doubter okay
can we go to the data of the data then
it becomes endless then it's like two
hours to get the pen going before you
went in the room and he's going to
discuss this problem it's called the
endless regression question okay
which means you should have been
thinking about the pen two years ago to
get it to be here by now because you got
to get the left side of the green and
the right side of the green then you got
to get the bottom of the left side of
the green the top of the lesson on the
green the bottom of the right side of
the green the bummer right
okay all right one more question who's
got one mr. mani man Issa when was the
first class who came to your historical
check there we go uh first one I'm just
curious
San Francisco eighteen yeah exactly
okay right after the earthquake and fire
ya know a while ago but it's been a
while since I've seen you and it's very
good to see you again and thank you for
teaching um I'd like to go back to the
earlier question about Buddha nature and
you said you know its inherent but it
doesn't mean it didn't come from you
which implies it comes from some harm
it's some karmic arising then and if
it's a karmic karmic arisings are
generally not unchanging things yeah and
so there's this little discontinuity
that I have
yeah and that's why we take questions
okay because it's a good question and
it's a famous question and it's coming
up in this text they're gonna discuss it
in this text but I'll I'll what do you
call it just in case we all died tonight
let's cover it okay so they're supposed
to be like three unchanging things in
the universe
chin obnoxious alpha male of a public
duty didn't such a country Daedalus
salmon Kentucky burger some elongate
diamond until machinima suyeon day I'll
be damned Akasha duma chain of suyeon
thing there are three unchanging things
in the universe what are they
am empty space which we're gonna discuss
in this text if we get there secondly
meaning the end of something happening
to you forever
okay at a certain point in understanding
the pen it is impossible to go to a
lower birth ever again
why does geshe michael keep repeating
the pen okay at a certain point in
understanding the pen it is impossible
to take a lower birth ever again okay
maybe I should teach it like three times
every time I give a talk okay
then then there's other sensations you
reach by seeing emptiness directly those
are the three things that cannot change
but emptiness is generally included in
there okay so if emptiness is something
that's unchanging
that means it cannot be coming from a
scene because anything that comes from a
stage shows a sine wave you see it girls
girls girls girls girls while the seed
is asserting its power and then as the
seed tires are the thing ends and so all
created things all things that come from
seeds show this sine curve okay so what
man is sayin is if emptiness is also
coming from my mind then how is it that
it can be unchanging and the classic
answer is to point to the Trevanian
Fountain in Rome
okay right Bengali fine nose I don't
know I was in Rome we gave it talking
room and they take you to some famous
fountain and it looks like just some old
tired tlaquepaque fountain and you know
you're like yeah okay then you try to
find a pizza place anyway the shape of
that or what's that thing at Yosemite
yeah when Old Faithful goes off the
water comes up and it splits and it goes
to each sign okay
so if you took three photographs in a
row the outline of the water would be
this mushroom shape okay so the water
the what do you call that thing the the
geyser is being fed by new seeds but the
outline doesn't change okay and that's
how they explain emptiness so emptiness
is flowing from my seeds like all other
objects in the universe but those seats
are always constant okay the shape they
make which is the lack of a husband who
didn't come from me
it's always this thing I can catch you
it's constant but constancy doesn't
imply inherent see because you can have
patterns that remain the same without
being not coming from you without not
not coming from okay
got it really I'm not just being cute
it's it's true okay it's a the pattern
is unchanging emptiness always looks the
same even though it's coming from you
and by the way is is the emptiness of
something eternal is it permanent
why yeah when the thing goes out of
existence the emptiness when the husband
dies the emptiness of the husband goes
out of existence okay so it's a mistake
to call emptiness permanent and and many
many Buddhist texts mistranslated so if
you open a book people are always giving
me Buddhist books I don't know why bad
translations it's inevitably just before
I get on a plane they hand me a heavy
translation you know and then I'm like
well thank you you know then after I get
through passport control I'll open it
it's called the what do you call it
Lancome test because there's always some
Lancome display right after the passport
control
so I pause in the Lancome I open it up
and if it says emptiness is permanent I
tossed the book then I don't feel guilty
I just tossed the book sometimes I leave
it on the Lancome display you know got
it okay so yeah Antonis is constant but
it's not necessarily eternal is eternal
that's eternal that's eternal constant
brought about come by your karmic seeds
and never changes
there's a few there's a few there's a
few cessations space and emptiness
there's like three okay from you okay
we're gonna stop there before you get to
something I can't answer and I will see
you at seven o'clock there's gonna be a
nice workshop this afternoon and don't
blow it off okay come to the workshop
because it's it's the application of
this stuff it doesn't do any use to come
to these classes if you don't use it
next week okay the goal next week is
that you are more aware of the
conversation in your mind and you are
actively trying to detect devil
appearances which okay look the
conversation in your mind all day
constitutes two things number one you
are trying to figure out how to get rid
of things or people you don't like
number two you are trying to figure out
how to get things or people you do like
all human mental conversation has two
subjects number one get something you
want number two get away from something
you don't want and that devil is always
there in both cases okay I will use
self-existent means to get rid of this
person I don't like I will use
self-existent means to get this goal I
want okay the only means that are not
self existent is how can I plan to say
to make this happen okay now if if we
were all perfect students and we went
through these three days and we
workshopped it together we practiced
right you're going to practice talking
wrong okay you're gonna practice saying
stupid things like oh you know I would
like to Mina I I'd like to meet someone
I can play music with okay
we need one more right and okay and then
let's see I should go to different
venues in Sedona or I should contact
friends I have in Sedona okay give me a
devil or angel okay ready here we go I
should I should look online demo I
should go to places where people play
music and see if I can hook up with
somebody
demo yeah maybe I should call my friend
who plays me thinking might know
somebody yeah I should help someone
miles find a friend who's trying to find
one angel got it but I the fact is each
of us who've been trained for years and
years we still think the old way so can
we put up a devil detector
shishun in your mind and then at least
at least object for a few seconds you
know you can't find another musician and
he's like yeah yeah okay and then then
you can have your normal thought process
okay the goal of this week is just to
object to it once in a while okay all
right thank you see you tonight
[Applause]